All right.
And we're starting the meeting.
I'm going to go ahead and admit everybody
in the lobby, OK?
And it's just going to take a second to
let everybody online in and all right,
I think we should be good.
Thank you, everybody.
This is Dominic Serlo with the Department
of Health Center for Medical Cannabis and
Psilocybin.
Thank you,
everybody for joining the meeting.
We have about 20 people,
maybe a little bit more here present with
us in the room.
And then quite a few people also online,
just as a reminder,
because we do post these these meetings
online.
Please watch your language to make sure
that nothing inappropriate is said.
And with that,
this is the end of life Care MIDI.
And I will pass it on over to Larry
Lehmann, the chair.
Larry, Thanks, Dominic.
Thanks somebody for coming here just like
an amazing turn out here and let people
online.
The reason we're doing this is a 1 and
everyone's been saying we need
conversations,
we need the ability to even talk and go
back and forth and but we need to do a
plan that we're gonna be open and such.
So it's hopefully super helpful standard
for is gonna do her presentation on
Hospice.
We then wrote up some questions that are
sort of questions floating out there for
for end of life for for discussion.
And then we have this for three hours,
You know, our meetings,
if we have endurance, we can do that.
And I was sort of thinking that's a long
time for a meeting that we'd probably end
closer to 3:30, but we'd have them.
Let me introduce some Jennifer Thompson.
He's from Red Willow Hospice Center who's
been in the Taos news recently about an
article about starting up.
And hopefully it's gonna tell them you'll
learn the first upside down at Hospice
centers in the country.
Thank you very much.
So should I do this?
Yeah, It's it's mainly for people online.
And if if you're able to hold it fairly
close to your mouth,
like the whole time I'm presenting,
if my if I can balance this.
OK.
So hello.
Can everyone see my screen?
OK, so let's get started.
Johnny gonna talk about psilocybin
therapy and wait one moment.
OK, Wait.
Sorry, Kathy, can you say that again?
Yeah, I got it now.
OK, cool.
Should I go back over here where he was?
That might be good, actually.
Hey, bear with us, guys.
All right?
Is that better?
All righty.
So First off,
I just want to thank Doctor Larry for
inviting me into this conversation.
I really appreciate the thoughtfulness
he's bringing to the work here in an exit
bill.
And I also want to say that I'm coming to
this both as a clinician and I'm aware
I'm in a room with deep expertise in the
psychedelic space.
And I don't assume that I have all the
answers.
I'm bringing my experience in Hospice,
in Hospice care,
my intuition and a beginner's mind.
There may be more questions than answers
and what I share, and I welcome that.
I see that this is a part of a a
collective learning process that we're
all in right now.
We're all in this together.
OK,
so approaching psychedelic facilitation,
I serve as a facilitator, not a healer.
My role and desire is to support the
relationship between the patient and
medicine without overly directing or
imposing,
facilitating a safe space for change and
providing tools and framework for that
change to occur.
As we bring this work into a western
medicine realm,
we must be careful not to over medicalize
and lose what makes it effective.
We must remember to teach those that we
are certifying into this work that we are
but hollow bones.
We are coming into this relationship not
to be healers,
but to facilitate the relationship
between patient and plant medicine or
molecule so that they can come into
greater alignment and relationship with
themselves.
Feel really strongly about this.
We have a unique opportunity in New
Mexico to look around at what has been
done in other States and how we can stay
true to the culture of our own state here.
So who I am,
I come to this work as a nurse and a
Hospice clinical director with a
background in sexual assault and
addiction treatment leadership.
I'm also deeply trained in trauma
informed and somatic approaches and have
studied spiritual and ceremonial
traditions that inform how I hold this
work in the spaces we facilitate.
I've been in recovery for 19 years and my
own experience with psilocybin over the
past eight years has been absolutely life
changing.
It has led me to train formally as a
psychedelic facilitator at Europa and to
create outdoor retreats focused on
embodiment and living fully.
I often think of these peak experiences
as small deaths,
moments where ego structures soften,
allowing people to come back to life with
more freedom and presence.
In my own healing journey,
at the root of my traumatized parts is
always the fear of annihilation and death.
I don't know if that makes sense to
anyone else.
Leaning towards the sphere has been
pivotal for me,
and integrating those parts into the
whole psychedelics can replicate this.
This is why I'm committed to bringing
this to patients at the end of life.
We can provide not just less suffering,
which these medicines do do,
but more aliveness and coolness while
they're still here.
Why this matters in Hospice.
So these medicines can help us relieve
existential distress, fear of death,
loss of meaning, disconnection.
Hospice manages physical pain well,
but existential suffering is often just
as profound.
Fear of death and loss of meaning are
central to drivers of distress,
and also relieving emotional suffering
can change the perception of pain.
Since I realize we're going to be able to
provide this modality at the end of life
clients to end of life clients,
I have realized the idea of getting to
provide a medicine that can lift the
right.
I'm sorry guys,
I'm like shaky and nervous.
I have relished the idea of getting to
provide a medicine that can lift
existential angst and suffering I see in
our clients and I feel really strongly
about it.
Great, thanks.
Usually I present things multiple times
before I do them in like crowds.
OK, So what psilocybin can offer,
And I feel like most of us in this room
know this,
but reduced anxiety and depression,
relief of death related anxiety and
distress, support for life review,
increased connectedness,
greater acceptance.
Psilocybin can help patients move toward
acceptance, connection,
and meeting at the end of life.
So 4 principles that I'm looking at in
Hospice related to psychedelic care,
comfort care, and relief of suffering,
which is a core Hospice principle set in
setting intention and integration,
trusting inner intelligence of the client
and the medicine relationship.
This work depends on the therapeutic
container preparation and integration are
oftentimes more important than the dosing
itself.
Therapeutic outcomes are closely tied to
the environment preparation and
integration,
not just the substance itself.
So just remembering as we're teaching
people that are coming into this medicine
work that those are really the most
important things in my my view,
a possible clinical model overview for
Hospice.
So you can use a lot of those.
I'm sorry, So what?
We would set up policies and procedures
written and integrated into Hospice model
care.
We would do screening and assessment,
interdisciplinary group reviews,
preparation sessions along with consent
process, dosing sessions, integration,
maybe 2 to 4 sessions and ongoing Hospice
care integrated into the entire process
entry and education.
So this will be introduced upon admission
in our admission packets,
ongoing patient education and voluntary
participation.
So we're not gonna make people trust and
Hospice OK screening and clearance.
So all of these are in alignment with
what Hospice does anyway for a lot of
different processes that we have in place
already.
So there would be a medical evaluation by
an MDMP on the team.
There would be a nursing assessment that
goes along with that, a medication review,
a psychological screening and an informed
consent process.
So interdisciplinary review,
which we call IDG.
So every two weeks,
core disciplines are required to be in
attendance.
And it's the,
it's the core disciplines of Hospice,
but also it usually involves the whole
team.
So the core disciplines are nursing,
medical providers, social work,
spiritual care,
and other disciplines are Cnas and
volunteers.
Hospices are required to have a team of
volunteers as a part of a Medicare
requirement,
which is really useful sometimes and
mental health support.
So our preparation phase,
I know what you said, what are you up to?
Sorry about that.
That's OK.
So our preparation phase I'm this is,
you know,
a lot of these things are my own
intuitive knowing feeling into this.
It's based on studies and clinical models,
but I'm thinking two or three sessions
which are as typical in models that we're
seeing, which includes intention setting,
education and expectations of the client
and emotional and existential preparation.
So in my personal practice,
it's my belief that the prep phase is
where I teach nervous system regulation
tools and tools that will will be
implemented in the integration phase as
well.
And these include breath work like simple
vase nerve breath, basic Tre,
trauma release exercises, and,
and I teach heart coherence meditations
and grounding practices as well in the
beginning phases.
It's been my experience that if we teach
these tools prior to medicine sessions,
that it gives the body and nervous system
permission and muscle memory to utilize
them during the sessions.
And that's been what's happened to me.
You know, like I,
I've practiced trauma release exercises
and I watch my body during medicine
sessions shape, you know, just releasing.
So this is just my, my opinion.
Dosing sessions and medicine journeys.
So those will of course be supportive
controlled environment of the home
environment.
There will be a trained facilitator
present with clinical support available
medical that means the medical and it
will be Co created patient centered
experience.
We can also look at the use of micro
dosing in end of life care,
which I'm going to talk a little bit more
about that in a second.
And so I'm in the the conscious
Physicians Psychedelic Academy right now
with doctor Leo Botany and I've had,
you know, some conversations with her.
And so the guidance that I've received
from her around medicine dosing is that
anywhere from 1g to 3 grams for end of
live patients could be beneficial.
And it really just depends on what phase
they're in, like what's what's going on,
which is to, you know,
we're always looking at the whole patient,
right?
So a medically unstable patient or
someone that's closer to the end of life
might not need to do a three grand
journey, right?
And in fact,
I think micro dosing can be amazingly
effective at that level of medicine.
It's effective for me.
You know,
I micro dosed for like 7 years with
therapy before I did a macro dose from,
you know, dip in when I was a kid.
But I think micro dosing can be a really
beautiful gift for end of life clients
and could be appropriate.
So those would be Co creative dreams and
we've been feeling that and the client
would feel into that, See how it goes,
clinical support considerations.
So during during journeys and throughout
the whole process,
we're going to be continuing palliative
care,
we're going to be doing symptom
management during all of it as well.
We're going to be monitoring as
appropriate.
A possible Hospice model could be that in
the evaluation and assessment of
medications and health status,
a plan is put in the place for pain
control and any other medical conditions
that may need to be addressed during the
medicine session.
So all hospices have a comfort kit of
medications in the home that are
available to patients as needed.
And families and caregivers are taught
how to use those medications to support
the client.
And they range from pain medications to
nausea and vomiting and agitation
medications.
And so we will of course,
be looking at what specific meds we might
want to have in place.
But really those comfort medications are
probably been, you know,
good for psilocybin journeys.
And I think those could be utilized there.
Advanced care planning and directives.
So this care is going to align with the
existing directives that the client has.
We're gonna have conversations during the
prep sessions and the consent sessions
around emergency planning discussions.
And we're gonna largely follow those
advanced directives, right?
And we're gonna respect the patient
wishes integration phase.
So follow up sessions we're gonna be
doing,
it's my feeling that a trained
integration person or a therapist should
fulfill this role.
I think the integration is pretty
important.
So I think, you know,
I'm going to have a whole team of people
that are going to have some experience in
training in these modalities.
But what I'm personally looking at is
having someone that really gravitates
towards it and has experience with
building space in that way.
Because the integration piece I'm finding
as, as you guys all know,
like the the biggest piece, you know,
you can do these drugs and have an effect,
but it's,
it's really not going to stick most
likely if we're not doing integration.
And I do question, you know,
these people are into play.
So maybe they are OK with just the short
burst,
but I still want to give them the
opportunity of having that full
experience of having that integration.
So in those integration phases where
we're looking at meaning making emotional
processing and support for the patient
and the family, Aspis strength.
So why this why this modality really is
gonna work well with Aspis?
We already have an interdisciplinary care
model.
We have spiritual care integration,
we have a family centered approach,
we have bereavement support and we have
volunteers available and those,
all of those things,
all of those structures are requirements
in Hospice.
And so it's a benefit for this modality.
And volunteers, we,
we have all different kinds of volunteers.
We have therapists, we have doulas.
So we can utilize those sorts of people
as well.
OK, so family and community.
So family inclusion when appropriated.
And I,
I have kind of a question like when is
that appropriate and is it possible in a
Hospice model to include family members?
And I'm really not sure about that
because the,
the dying person is our patient and we,
you know,
we do provide bereavement services and
counseling services for family members
and support in that way.
We wrap around family in that way,
but I am not certain that we are going to
be able to figure out how to do any sort
of medicine sessions with family members
unless it's outside the Hospice model.
You know,
we could help facilitate aligning them
with someone like a doula or some other
facilitator to be able to participate in
that way.
It's a question.
So safety considerations.
So most risks can be mitigated with
thoughtful screening,
medication review and clinical oversight.
And I think that we want to remember the
the goals of Hospice or comfort and
relief of suffering.
And so looking at these interactions with
these medications from that framework,
not wanting to exacerbate anything and
not being too conservative as well.
So I guess I can go through these a
little bit.
So the SSRIs and the SNR is often don't
cause harm,
but may dampen the therapeutic effect.
MAOIS can intensify effects,
so require caution.
Antipsychotics can block the experience.
Benzos are useful as a rescue medication,
but reduce the depth.
Mood stabilizers effects vary and that's
kind of a case by case basis.
Stimulants which Hospice patients are
generally not on stimulants can increase
anxiety or cardiovascular strain.
Opioids, which are common in Hospice,
are generally competitive compatible,
but we just need to monitor those for
sedation, which again,
we're going to weigh, you know,
what are we looking at for the patient in
Hospice in cardiac meds,
Sometimes Hospice patients are on cardiac
meds and it's just important to module
vitals, especially in VP.
But again,
we're not lifesaving in Hospice.
And these people are gonna go through a
consent process and be really informed
about that.
Yeah.
And so all of that, I feel,
is weighed with discussions of advanced
directives and patient goals,
safety considerations.
So psychological screenings,
this is really about meeting the patient
where they're at and creating the safest
possible container.
We're gonna screen for psychotic
disorders, screen for bipolar,
bipolar disorder,
evaluate suicidality and safety risk,
trauma history with support planning,
cognitive status, dementia and delirium.
So obviously those types of patients are
not able to consent.
So we're going to run up against that and
probably not be able to provide the
service for Hospice patients,
social support and environment and
clarified expectations and intentions.
And again,
just remembering that the goal of Hospice
is relief of suffering and comfort.
And so, you know,
Larry and I were briefly talking about
this right before I started talking and
we're going to scream for these things
and just weigh what would cause more
comfort or less comfort.
So timing considerations,
there's no clear evidence based cut off.
We're going to individualize and look at
our clinical judgment potential benefit
across all stages of illness.
And so this is this timing thing.
This is something that I've thought of
often and Linea up to the end of life
care is that patients may or may not come
back from this journey.
And in the consent process,
how do we talk about that?
And we'll make sure that we're more truth
telling.
So I would probably talk about it as I do
anything in Hospice,
which is just really compassionate and
open truth telling and just, you know,
I think,
I think it is something that we need to
talk about, you know,
that your soul or your body might not
come back from this journey and we're
following your advanced directors.
Is that OK?
So that is just my opinion,
the thought on that implementation
considerations.
So workforce training and requirements
and these are these are these are
questions,
these are questions that are out there.
What licensing pathways are we going to
need to utilize care settings?
So at this time, so home versus facility.
So most patients in Hospice are either at
home or in like a Alf or a skilled
nursing facility.
And at this time,
all of our care will be in home settings
because I have no idea at this point like
if facilities are going to let us do this
medicine in the facility and I would
suspect they probably won't.
So most likely they'll mostly be in homes,
documentation standards.
I think all hospices are going to handle
this in their own ways.
This is not going to be a Medicare
covered program at this point.
And so policies are going to be policies
are going to be specific to individual
hospices and putting in assets.
So this is not going to be a Medicare
funded therapy,
which Medicare is our main payer source.
I believe that grant funding will be
pivotal in access and Hospice clients
will obviously not be charged for this
service at least maybe it's not obvious,
but Hospice clients will most likely not
be charged.
And we are looking at utilizing grant
funding in our nonprofit arm to fund this
work,
ongoing fundraising for it and use of
doula as an outside facilitators as
supports.
So these services in a Hospice setting
will most likely be cash pay by family
and integrated into the care team.
We are able to use doula as volunteers.
So we had a doula that was on staff that
was trained as a facilitator and wanted
to help with this.
That would be great.
But in practice,
a lot of families in Northern New Mexico,
I'm not, you know,
I would love to use more doulas,
but it is a cash pay process usually
outside the Hospice care model.
And so it's dependent on their their
income and their wealth on whether or not
they can do that.
So that is also a question that's out
there for me.
So key policy questions,
who is able to provide this care?
So these are like the actual questions
that we're here to kind of answer and
what training standards are required and
how is access insured across rural areas?
And actually,
I think this is sort of an easy one
because hospices are ideally suited to
provide care across rural areas.
We're,
we're stretched out all over the place in
homes, out in the middle of nowhere.
And I, I think it'll be,
that'll be an easy piece,
like we'll get to provide that access.
And how are cultural spiritual practices
included?
And I'll just comment on that.
Like, in my opinion and experience,
like I want to Co create whatever that
client and family want to do.
And that's what we do in Hospice anyway
with our spiritual care practices.
And we're going to facilitate exactly,
you know,
whatever we can do for them that will
make them most safe and comfortable.
So I do work for Red Below Hospice and I
just thought I'd put a plug in for,
for our company.
We are an integrative holistic community
based teaching Hospice.
We serve rural and underserved
populations within a A50 mile radius
radius around Taos in Santa Fe and
Albuquerque.
We have a whole person care model.
We have a maid support program.
And this model is grounded in real
Hospice work in northern New Mexico.
This last slide,
Doctor Larry sent out that e-mail this
morning with some questions that he had.
And so I created a slide for him so that
we can kind of have this up.
And that's all I have.
Does anybody any questions or comments?
Thank you for your time and attention.
Hi, I'm Daniel.
Jeez.
Hi, I'm Danielle Slupeleki.
I I'm an end of life doula and I'm also
the executive director of the New Mexico
Debtor Network.
So when you bring a game for doulas,
we have a provider reimbursement program.
So any eligible provider that gives end
of life care,
we will pay the provider directly.
When the family cans, we do $50.
00 an hour up to 30 hours per patient,
up to two clients per provider per year.
So we're actively working to make sure
that everybody has access to additional
support outside of Hospice.
It's the New Mexico Dental Care Network.
There are rack cards and business cards
over here and we've also created an end
of life planner that I would love to get
into the hands of all Hospice patients.
If we order 50 or more at a time,
the cost is $5 each.
And so if that's something that we can
get grants for, it enhance everybody.
It's got places to put your your advance
directive information,
who to contact when you die,
how to take care of your pets,
where are your passwords,
how are your bills paid,
all of the good stuff.
So just know that we're actively working
towards making sure everybody gets
covered with that.
So thank you.
I was thinking, yeah, Jennifer,
thanks for your presentation and good,
I think we're all so excited about what
you're doing up in with Red Willow.
I know,
and you have a great just to give this a
little bit of structure,
I thought maybe what we could do is focus
the first set of questions and not get a
presentation about Hospice.
Then maybe we can shift you over into
some of those questions if we can make
the figures of the e-mail or something.
But that that felt like something to do
right now.
But OK,
but I wanted to ask you one question.
You know, I'm used to Hospice having,
you know,
Medicare 6 month limit and I'm wondering
how what you guys are thinking about that.
I mean, you know, I think that, you know,
clearly people's reading process or
healing process for transformation,
you know,
just start feeling they haven't diagnosed
and there's and have any thing here is
I'm wondering how you see red will work
with that or what you think about other
programs to be a certain people that have
a longer horizon.
Do you want people to have the mic or not?
Yeah, well,
we are constrained by a terminal
diagnosis in that time frame.
It doesn't,
it does not necessarily mean that if a
person gets a terminal diagnosis of six
months or less that they will actually
only be on the service for that time.
Oftentimes people are on service for
years.
You know,
I mean that's not ideal for a Medicare
Hospice model,
but in practice it does happen that way
because we're de prescribing,
we're giving them more care.
They actually tend to do better for a
while.
So it is, you know,
clients could potentially come on service
and,
and get this modality and be able to be
on service longer and receive more
treatment.
But in general,
we are constrained by Medicare and
needing to recertify every medicine.
And you know,
say that they have a terminal diagnosis
and this is their their symptoms.
I mean all of that that answer your
question Yeah yeah.
So so yeah,
I I think it brings up the question,
you know are are there ways to expand
beyond that you know model in the
community is to be able to you know work
with people sooner sooner than that and
somehow then maybe maybe be alive maybe
the Hospice adjacent like ways to to work
with you yeah.
I think maybe integrating private you
know doulas and facilitators.
Thank you.
Is this on?
No,
I maybe integrating private facilitators
and doulas into palliative care programs,
you know,
and just networking and making
connections with people prior to going on
to Hospice.
So palliative care is usually before
Hospice.
And yeah,
it probably would have to be private
people using like equity funds unless
we're going to allow insurance someday.
Yeah, I'll hand it.
I'm Jamie Beachy.
I'm a former Hospice chaplain and
spiritual care person.
Also was one of the Co founders of the
Naroka training program,
I think before you got here.
But my question is about assessment.
How are you planning to assess and
evaluate who's appropriate for the,
the psilocybin intervention?
I mean,
spiritual distress and existential
distress and demoralization seems like a
good reason to consider this for, for a,
a person.
But what are you ruling out other than,
you know, medical contraindications?
And how are you, how are you deciding who,
who's good for this intervention?
I don't think we're going to rule out
that much because it's really going to be
the medical considerations because people
in end of life in general are grappling
with that transition.
All of them.
Like nobody's leading up to death.
I mean,
I would maybe 1% of people are OK with
their death.
And so, yeah.
And Katrina,
this is my clinical director in
Albuquerque.
But I mean,
are there reasons you're saying that
people shouldn't, you know,
work with silicide is not the right ask?
No,
I think as somebody coming into the
psilocybin world and loving Hospice,
we're all appropriate.
When you take a journey,
you realize things that are kind of
locked within, within you.
And you didn't think you had those big
traumas or huge histories.
But at the end of life,
everything wears its ugly head and gets
in the in the way of like a peaceful
journey out of this life.
So we're all appropriate.
It's just offering options that people
have that have been stigmatized and
educating people on how it can help them.
The other piece is that because this
isn't a Medicare regulated program,
we don't have those constraints around
having to qualify someone.
And really I think we're gonna wait and
see what the constraints might be through
the legislation,
through the roles of pathways that we're
cementing in right now.
But other than a a pretty severe
psychological or you know,
diagnosis or dementia that they can't
consent even a severe cardiac issue,
we I think we could still utilize this
medicine in ways even if it's a lower
dose, you know, micro dose,
things like that.
And it's really sort of patient dependent,
you know,
like what is their advanced directive
situation?
Are they OK with utilizing this
medication with the risks as long as
their consent aim?
Yeah,
I'm just curious what where your thinking
is on it right now.
You know, I mean,
I think there must be people that maybe
are not appropriate for it for any
reasons, you know,
just in case they have too much trauma in
their background, they're, you know, yeah.
So those psychological screenings and,
you know,
the medical screenings will be the main
thing.
But I don't think that we're,
I guess what I'm thinking is that we're
not coming up against having to qualify
them for an insurance issue.
So we can look at it on a case by case
basis.
Thank you for your presentation, Jenna.
It was fantastic.
I was enroute from you when I was there.
Thank you.
Just as a reminder,
just to introduce yourself as well.
Sorry, yes, no, you're good.
It's nice to meet you all in person.
Always, always.
And I love the questions that you're
asking.
You know,
I have seen complex childhood traumas,
especially at them of life,
where the limit you're in that liminal
state, they come forward.
And then if you add on a psychedelic,
you re trauma.
If I'm saying and so as you know,
Jen is mentioning that process of
education concern that may be a long time
before somebody at the is appropriate.
And I see that trauma therapy in the
state of state of preparation to be on
great value account essential.
You know,
narcissistic personality is heart
conditions.
You may have a heart attack during the
the ingestion.
The patient may not die,
but they might be having migraine
emotions and having a consent saying that
if you die during the experience,
are you OK with that?
And what procedures do you want to take
during that time?
That's important.
Having medications to spy,
to take that Nitro when they need it,
you know,
but I think it's the it's the assessment
part and really that feeling that a
facilitator also has with a person.
If they're not ready, they're not ready,
whether no boy or not, mommy,
that's super important not to push an
agenda, disable.
You have to heal before you go on,
you know, no,
like you can be traumatize people and
create more complications for them.
So thank you for that balanced question,
because if it's not,
I don't see psychos being, you know,
and with the executive order coming in,
that's what, you know, really concerns me.
I think it's awesome and it's scary.
I think we need to hold both sides of of
the of the same coin and be very
conscious and intentional in how you
proceed.
How kind of low that we already have here.
Hi, everyone.
Really, really grateful to be here today.
My name's Denali Wilson.
I am the director of strategic support
for the Healing Advocacy Fund and based
on Las Cruces.
I just wanted to it's coming up in a lot
of subcommittees and now that our ideas
about it are taking more shape,
I don't want to derealize too much,
but wanted to talk really briefly about
insurance.
The Healing Advocacy Fund is partnering
with Akita back there and the US
Psychedelic Mental Health Access Alliance
to get this,
to get the answer to this question
because New Mexico has a unique
opportunity as the first medically
integrated model to look at it
differently.
And it is true that components of the
care will not be covered until there's
FDA approval and even then with natural
medicine will not be covered.
But so much of the care that we know it
as being incredibly critical to,
to the positive outcomes are prep and
integration work,
that those are services that Medicaid and
Medicare are already covering in other
circumstances.
And so as long as we are really,
really thoughtful,
like I don't wanna be so Pollyanna about
it that it's gonna be easy.
It's not gonna be easy.
It's gonna be from the regulations we
write to the way that we're operating
billing to the way that we are
structuring our legal entities, right?
Like it touches all of those points.
But I,
I do believe that it's possible for a lot
of the,
the care to be covered by not just
Medicaid, Medicare,
but our then our commercial third party
payers.
And I'm really committed to,
to making sure that we democratize that
information and help support providers
who,
who want to want to integrate that into
their existing clinical and and billing
framework.
So be sure to connect and we can continue
to talk.
Something else that I was going to say
about this, I may be forgotten,
but I'll come back to it.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Hi, I'm Sky Rivers,
I'm with the Santa Fe reporter.
I've been covering this from the very
beginning.
Story will be coming out soon.
What we've come up with in the meantime,
I have a question for you.
You did a lovely job.
Thanks.
We're talking about trauma and what comes
up with psilocybin, which I've heard.
There was a woman we went to the
psychedelic convention and she had a
whole,
she was a therapist for 25 years joints,
I don't remember the name of Alban,
but she was talking about this whole
other side of consciousness that
different tapping into then taking
psilocybin and imprinting trauma that
you're talking about it.
You're therapist went traumatized and
blah, blah, blah.
Then you take the psilocybin and well,
then comes up she was talking about a
whole other side of it.
So my question to you is,
have you found end of life patients or
some of them go into their journey that
they've can the psilocybin facilitate the
after journey like this?
Bring forth that part of the journey
where you're like.
Oh my, your fear drops, your trauma drops,
everything drops,
but yet you're like connected to a bigger
picture.
And then they bring it forth when they
come out of it, if they're lucky enough.
And I wanted to know if you have that,
they bring what forth?
Whatever they experienced in the journey,
which was a positive journey,
like didn't they come back?
I'm not afraid anymore.
My God,
whatever they connected into the source.
Have you had experiences with end of life
patients who have brought that into it
outside of Toronto?
I have had personal experiences with that
and that's why I wanna do this work
because I feel like, I mean,
when we go into these journeys,
we are connecting with all that is at
least I should speak for myself, you know,
I have felt connected that to all that is
and all of the things.
Everything else seems like small stuff,
right?
And So what you're saying like it all
just kind of drops and we come back and
we're more open, we're more connected.
One of the things I think about a lot is
that I used to specialize in addiction
and they, we talk about an addiction,
that the remedy for addiction is
connection.
And I really think that connection and
that feeling of connected to all it is,
is kind of the remedy for all of us as
well.
And so that's really why I want to bring
this work forth exactly,
kind of what you just said.
Have you had a lot of patients come forth
with any of that?
We're just mostly under trauma they were
dealing with.
And that and share with everyone that
I've experienced has had that experience
of kind of like having a little bit of
that drop and, you know,
like being more open, being more flexible.
Their ego structure is relaxing.
And so that's sort of for me,
the whole point is to have that feeling
of more connection.
Yeah.
Hello, my name is Hanifa Nile Washington.
I'm coming from Santa Fe today.
Thank you so much everyone for convening
this hybrid meeting.
Your presentation was wonderful,
really inspiring.
And so I am the Co director of the
Psychedelic mental health access alliance.
I'm also a healer and I've been
supporting healing spaces with mostly
psilocybin and women for about 15 years.
And I do a lot of other things too.
But just to give context,
I'm really curious about your vision and
when you're envisioning for how people go
about the education process, right?
Because this is so important in terms of
how do we inform these clients and people
transitioning about this experience,
what it is, what it's not,
what's possible as well as their families.
And so I'm very curious in terms of help
informing the families and then how to
support the families as through that
through this kind of additional layer of
supporting their loved 1.
You might not have all the answers,
but I'm just curious about like your
vision of what will some of those
education tools and processes look like?
OK, thank you for that question.
So this is something that's kind of
rolling out in our minds as we speak.
We're working on creating, you know,
those assets right now.
But what I sort of feel into is that it's
going to be like some other processes we
already have in place.
So we're we're kind of doing education
out in the community.
We're going to different healthcare
places, different places and doing,
you know, in services,
those sorts of things in our admission
packets, you know,
we're going to have A1 pager on it and go
over it.
And then if there's an opening or in
interest,
then we can dive a little deeper into
that process.
I have personally, you know,
written up some education pamphlets
around these therapies.
And so like I said,
we're kind of in process on how to do
that education.
But I think it's going to be a pretty
extensive process.
They'll be, you know,
in my experience in being a healthcare
worker in RN,
we need to reeducate sort of over and
over again.
You know,
we're gonna we're gonna talk about it,
you know,
in the admission or maybe they're gonna
hear about it in the community.
And then we're gonna do like an intro,
you know,
level education session where we're kind
of going over what the process of a
higher overview might look like and then
delving in layers, you know,
and this is just sort of how you educate
patients.
And then you might have to come back,
you know,
a couple more times and talk about it
more and more and do more deeper
education.
And then even when you're going into the
assessment phase of, you know,
bringing in like nursing assessment and,
and medical people and psychological
assessment, we're we're re education,
re educating the whole way, right?
So, and then the consent process.
So, you know, really going through,
you know,
informed consent in medical models is a
paper,
a set of paper forms like a contract
almost where you're really delineating
what the risks are and what the effects
might be and what you might feel.
And as much as we can educate on that,
we will do so in those informed consent
processes.
I wanna what we're personally looking at
for our model,
it's looking at ways not to lose people
in that education process and that
marketing process and all of that.
You know, we don't want to,
we wanna bring people in rather than
exclude, you know,
pushing away with our message.
And so we're working on that right now as
a team, trying to figure that out.
This is wonderful to hear.
And I, I mean, I,
I think about the families and depending
on the timeline, right,
of like someone making that transition,
the families, you know,
sitting and being with their dear ones
and loved ones,
the training and support that they will
need to provide that extra layer of
listening and presencing, right?
And so I wonder about things like the
Zendo project, for example,
providing some sort of like Hospice
family loved one sort of transition care
type of thing.
I just wonder about providing like,
it obviously could be optional for people
to like have that type of training and
they feel like they want that extra
support as they're like holding their
dear one as they're transitioning.
Then they've been assisted by this part
of, of the medicine in whatever way.
So I just wanted to name that.
Yeah,
I imagine that there's space for
collaboration in those ways.
In a lot of ways, like I said,
it's gonna be a Co creation of that
client's journey and what level of
involvement they want their family
members to be.
And of course there will be some level of
education to the family, you know,
and I think that we'll again,
Co create that experience.
I would love to figure out a way to be
able to provide some level of integration
with the family as well.
Haven't quite figured.
I'm thinking personally about groups in
the community, you know,
for family members outside in the Hospice
model, things like that.
Kenny,
are there any other questions online?
I'm gonna go here.
I mean, I feel we're good online.
Thank you, Jorge.
I did remember what I was going to say.
It wasn't anything bigger earth
shattering though.
So this is Denali again.
I was just going to say in general,
we're that New Mexico, we're,
we're really lucky to have a state
Medicaid office that is at one at the
table, right,
a part of the Advisory Board and already
committed to making sure the parts that
they can make work will.
And I think that that'll be a really
exciting model for,
for the rest of our insurance spaces.
And then the,
the the equity fund is such a critical
piece for covering the parts of care that
can't be covered by insurance or as we're
talking about family members or other
auxiliary supports that won't fit under a,
a traditional payer care model,
then that'd be critically important.
And that was that was it.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Hello.
Hey, my name is Lance Carroll.
And what a great presentation.
And I'm just wondering,
how many current patients do you have or
you've been asked a lot to start the
psychedelic assisted therapy during
Hospice care.
Have you had a lot of demand?
There has not been a lot of demand yet.
We haven't really done any blanket
education on it.
We just had a couple newspaper articles
come out in the last like month and I've
gotten maybe 4 phone calls this week.
So that's kind of big.
I've had therapists and doctors and
nurses kind of coming out of the woodwork,
though, wanting to work for me.
And that's been like, whoa, OK.
So I imagine once we have not started
marketing or kind of really talking about
it yet.
So I don't,
I have no idea how big this program will
be.
I have no idea what the demand's gonna be.
Well, and I know like,
we're family support,
the Hospice support teams or the support
groups afterwards have been really brave
behind them.
So I think really with the agreement
support.
Yeah.
So even that place for that for the
families.
Totally.
Yeah.
So Hospice is required to provide a year
of bereavement support by by Medicare.
So yeah, thank you.
Hello, Danielle Slupensky again.
You just brought up a question for me.
Since Hospice Prime got 13 months of
bereavement care,
can we somehow work in brief support
dosing sessions for a family?
I think then not immediately,
like right after the loss,
but somewhere in that 13 months.
It makes such a difference,
makes such a difference in the things
that I've seen folks that have used
medicines and worked that way,
it's completely changed their grief
process because, again,
they have a direct experience that
connects you to everything, you know.
So I would love to get grief as part of
our program.
That would be amazing.
Yeah.
Hello, everyone.
James Brown here.
Great presentation.
Thank you so much for sharing the space
and all your information with us.
Just a follow up on administration day.
So on your journeys,
experiences with your Hospice patients,
what other amazing treatment modalities,
healing modalities do you compass or
coral reef and can you share and expand
on that,
you know to to make sure that we do
hopefully include a lot of those
potential things.
Yes, thank you.
Yeah, so,
so I'm looking at Lita because her whole,
her whole bag is conscious life practices.
And and I also we're in alignment that
way.
I,
we all feel that building in these
practices is really paramount to the
success of the therapy and also just to
being a whole human.
So meditation, breath work,
like it can be really breath work that's
really simple,
like just expanding your lower belly and
stimulating your biggest nerve.
Journaling huge for me for integration.
Journaling is one of the biggest pieces,
you know,
drawing afterwards for integration,
trauma release exercises,
somatic practices, biohacking,
so nutrition, sweat lodge, you know,
heat therapy, cold therapy, exercise.
So really you're building a whole human
life practice, you know,
as much as you can.
And if we can sneak in for end of life
patients,
even a small fraction of those practices,
it's gonna improve their life like so
much.
Lita tells a story about just getting,
you know,
a patient to just eat better and drink
more water and that just totally changing
their experience at the end of their
lives.
And I know for me it those all these
practices are a full time job for me and
I wouldn't have it any other way.
And so I think getting as many of those
two end of life patients as we can,
I mean within reason because they are
having terminal illness.
But yeah, does that answer your question?
Same one we have some.
Thank you.
You know, I've seen.
Thank you so much.
What I've seen is, you know,
you brought up,
it's such a such great conversation here
with families.
I love the post death journey.
That's fantastic idea.
And also if we were able to get in on
palliative patients before they meet
Hospice criteria,
the unfortunate part about it is that
palliative medicine doesn't take anybody.
That's why it does not exist.
OK, we have it here and there.
We have it.
You know, it comes back and forth.
It's just the government doesn't pay for
it, which is really unfortunate.
But that is the moment I would say for a
patient to be talked about, you know,
to at education,
whether they have their whereabouts,
they have and still an understanding of
this world and the dementia really
dementia basis.
And perhaps, you know,
starting the education there with the
family and maybe opening their eyes to
the possibility of being with their
family even in a very small dose session.
That could change so much.
And then I usually go in not even with
medicine,
but when I go in for admit for on
admission for Hospice patients with ABQ
Hospice,
I am standing there talking about
forgiveness with the family members as
the patient is dying and that changes
their entire like lifetime of stuff alike.
Forgive yourself,
forgive them and and we sit in that
frequency together and that by itself is
a whole different place that they they
were at.
And oftentimes the patient is able to let
go with much more ease and much quicker
than they would have,
especially the transitional patients.
So in that patient,
we're not talking about medicine at all,
right?
And with the family are really not.
So these other practices like, hey,
how are you taking care of yourself with
the family members?
Are you drinking water?
Are you standing in the sun for like 10
minutes a day?
And that changes their life too.
But you know what you're mentioning I had
a physician mom with end stage pancreatic
cancer had gone through it for two years
with Whittle and chemotherapy with
everything.
She had a six year old son,
husband is a lawyer.
All she wanted was to be able to play
with the son and go to the farmers market,
make little bracelets and sell them with
him and she because every week,
twice a week,
we had to go to the hospital to get IV
therapy.
By the time we got connected,
she was in metastasized everywhere.
They,
she did not meet criteria for any other
MD Anderson clinical trials.
And she was cooped up in her room,
in the massive bedroom.
All the windows were shut.
Everything she had shut out the world.
And she would cry all day.
She had so much anxiety about dying.
And we did.
We started with hydration.
We started with changing her medic diet.
Her albumin came up because she started
eating more meat.
Simple things, right?
But they're huge for our Physiology.
She stopped having to go to the hospital
twice a week to get high rehydration.
She was now going every three weeks.
She was given a diagnosis of prognosis of
three months.
She lived another 12 months and we micro
dosed and that changed everything.
She went and going back with her child
outside.
They they did the thing with sitting with
her husband at the farmers market selling
their bracelets that they had made.
And she did die, but she lived.
She lived the last 12 months of her life
and she was present with her child and
with her husband.
And it was really thought, see,
and it was not a macro dose.
She couldn't tolerate A macro dose.
That's why, you know,
I know at state level, everybody's like,
stop talking about microdosing because
it's not in the bill.
And I understand.
But maybe in the future we can talk about
it.
But it is powerful medicine.
Thank you.
Thanks, Lena.
That forgiveness piece is beautiful.
Oh also just oh,
this is not just housekeeping thing.
Real quick did if anybody hasn't signed
in,
if you could just raise your hand and
I'll bring the same in chief part in.
Hi there.
My name is Trina Zaler and my my voice is
barely coming back online.
I'm a clinical social worker in Hospice
and palliative care and I appreciate the
conversation about, you know,
how do we help people access this prior
to Hospice?
But I think that that is the, the,
the biggest opportunity and the most
important place and they're, you know,
on the process.
And we do live in a state with very
limited access to palliative care.
And so then I started thinking about
where are the specialties that are really
important for the state program to do
outreach and education now to oncology,
nephrology, neuroscience.
And these are the basis where they're
consulting us in palliative care to try
to help people when they're in this place
with this stress.
And really,
so I'm really waiting until someone
really needs Hospice care before they
actually get into our palliative clinic.
So my hope is that the program.
Will include outrageous education to
specialty medicine clinics and also have
some way of helping them to connect to
medical and behavioral health clinicians
who can do exactly what Amy was bravery
to having that that thorough clearance to
make sure that someone is appropriate for
the same for it that will help all those
additions and the specialties although
feel comfortable giving this information
to their their clients.
So thank you for everyone sharing their
their information in there and bringing
back.
Hi,
my name is Michael Williams and you know,
one of the things that I was thinking
about in your talk is this idea of
different teams at different phases and
days of, you know, pre work,
charity work integration.
And because we don't have the
restrictions that a research study has,
I feel that education around what could
show journey informed pre consultation
with not only patient but also the family
and really giving navigating skills and
building rapport and building trust and
being human is probably one of the most
important things for a successful outcome.
And that I kind of feel like that person
in a pretty consultation should be
facilitated on the journey day and during
the integration.
My own personal opinion,
it's kind of hard to imagine of
facilitation coach,
I mean in and not being there and and we
think of the journey interpreting what
showed up and was felt and almost said
and only because we have the opportunity
to not have the guidelines that a
research study has.
And this is all in relationship to
successful outcomes of the treatment.
I just think that having the right person
to really be human and connected and have
report most important thing confidence,
trust is built before the actual journey
day to talk a little bit about that.
I totally agree.
And my thought is that we're going to
have,
we are training our staff at this time
for facilitator trainings.
But in practice,
I think we're gonna identify who those
people on our teams are that are
gravitating towards this work.
And that person is gonna be involved from
start to finish.
And it will be the person that, you know,
most gravitates towards it.
I think you know,
and it's most likely not gonna be 1 of
the nurses.
You know, it might be,
but I have people on staff, you know,
we have spiritual care coordinators,
we have social workers,
and I'm bringing counselors on that are
specifically steeped in integration.
So my hope is that, you know,
at each location there are a few people
that are able to hold this work and we'll
be there through the process.
So I agree with you.
The one part that I mentioned was
navigating skills with people who are
familiar with what can show up what and
how to navigate those different ways that
it shows up in different times and spaces.
And you know,
journey itself is I've found really
helpful when it does show up for the
person in the experience.
They have toolkit that they can utilize
and navigating whether it's all
challenging or you know,
upkeep experience or spiritual experience.
This none of us can know or can say
what's gonna show up, you know?
And so they give them a broad education
of what could show up and having tools at
the disposal.
What it does.
I think this is really work.
Something that should probably be
discussed more than I hear so.
But thank you.
Thank you.
Really enjoy.
That's an issue.
Oh, hey.
Oh, that's working out OK.
That's fine.
We've got somebody online who's gonna
speak.
But I actually need to adjust one thing
with the audio real quick before we do
that.
So Chris Caldwell,
just hang on a second and we'll get to
you.
I don't have nailed.
I'm Lockwood.
All right, Chris,
your mic should be enabled.
All right, you can hear me.
Hi, this is Chris Caldwell,
founder and executive director of End of
Life Psychedelic Care.
Jennifer,
thank you for that wonderful presentation.
I've been trying to remember all the
questions that were on Larry's slide or
your slide,
and so I'd like to make a few comments
and then I have a few questions for Larry
and whomever else can answer them.
First off,
you had talked about education and I
think of that from 2 two standpoints.
You talked a little bit about the need to
educate the community.
That's something that we've been doing to
several thousand people over the course
of the last few years.
Clearly a need people want to learn about
this.
And I, I'm,
I'm not sure if New Mexico has set aside
an educational fund.
That would be cool if they did.
If they didn't,
it's still a necessary component here to
educate on you all members of the
community.
And then secondly, you had,
you had an idea of 15 extra hours for end
of life psychedelic training and Larry
and Kate and Jen,
you all took the my core course.
And you know, that was the core course.
And there's several other courses where
we do deeper dives,
like we're doing one on grief and
spirituality.
And so, yeah, 15 hours.
I don't necessarily want to say it should
be 15 hours,
but I would love the opportunity to dive
more into that.
But this gets at the, you know,
some of the questions I've heard before
about how do you train individuals to do
this work specifically.
But I also wanted to ask, like I said,
Larry, or whomever can answer this,
has there ever been a list compiled of,
let's say,
chaplains who are already trained as
psychedelic facilitators?
Because that would be a great place to
start.
Which reminds me of the other question
you raised, Larry,
which is can a spiritual person be the
sole support?
And I would say, given your, the,
the legislation in the law,
can't that be a clinical chaplain trained
as a psychedelic facilitator?
And then the other sort of question I
have a couple of folks have brought up
and Lita, yeah,
definitely palliative care,
whether whether they're actually enrolled
in palliative care or they're eligible or
quite frankly,
anybody who believes that they need this
therapy should be able to be included.
And is what's the issue around?
Why not any, any individual?
Is it the place of service?
So I didn't quite understand if there
would be any issues beyond what Jennifer
was talking about, you know,
supporting Hospice patients out of an A
Hospice agency.
Lots of good questions there, Chris.
Let me turn the button on Larry.
Let me get questions there,
Chris and I very much enjoyed your your
training.
I'm not sure I could be the one that
answered all those questions,
but I think one of the the issues that it
was it was one of the ones on the the
last slide with questions was to just
step back a little bit and look at the
difference between what end of blind care
is of the other three conditions.
And give ourselves some spaciousness to
think that we can produce a program for
random life that may be different.
It may not be the same as the conditions
of depression and PTSD and and substance
use.
And that's one reason why put there other
question about requiring specific
training for a parent of end of life care.
I think that's it's worth thinking what
what should we require?
You know,
like so much of this word sort of
balancing a little bit of the what is the
optimal training,
skilled care and and also trying to have
access.
I mean,
if you're looking at a small town in,
you know, southern New Mexico, you know,
we're probably not going to have a
psychedelic chap on there,
but we should have somebody with some
access to spiritual training.
So that's that'll be on the map.
But as as we talk about this,
I would just think that we should really
try to see how much we can think about it
as being a little bit different than the
other diagnostics.
And this is Dominic Serlo and Chris.
Thank you again.
As to your initial question about a
compilation of individuals who have that
training and who are are able to do this
from the spiritual and religious
standpoint,
we to my knowledge there is not one at
this time.
However, as the program launches,
individuals who and practitioners who
want to be involved in providing the care
are going to need to register because
we're going to permit that.
And so as that occurs,
we will be able to track that and be able
to then have that available.
So just to to be able to let you know,
as far as I'm aware of, not at this time,
but we will have one when the program is
launching and we'll be keeping that up to
date.
This is Kate Hawk.
Yeah.
Along the lines of what Larry was saying,
end of life care isn't actually a
diagnosis in itself in the same way as
the other conditions.
And I mean,
Senator Steinborn was on one of our calls
and he confirmed that it was and he's
here today.
Hey.
And I, I don't remember,
he confirmed that it was left.
You know, that wording was intentional,
open.
And it doesn't mean we're trying to get
away with things,
but we also don't want to limit ourselves
unnecessarily.
So it's wonderful that there's not only
Hospice,
but there's maybe the most qualified
psychedelic we oriented Hospice in the
country right here.
So that's a wonderful resource.
Yeah, I don't know of any others.
I know.
I know you're leaders in any case.
And so that's, you know,
there's so many resources there already.
And you know, if we started, well,
here's what's being provided through that.
It doesn't mean that it's limited to
Hospice.
Nobody's saying this.
It's limited to Hospice,
but Hospice provides so many of the
things that we do want,
even if it's not in a Hospice setting.
I just want to mention on micro dosing,
there's nowhere it says no micro dosing,
but what it does say is there has to be
preparation,
there has to be an approved setting,
there has to be, you know, integration.
But if people are already getting
intensive services in Hospice, you know,
we could look at that more closely.
So great.
Apologies for being a my hog.
Danielle Lupes here again.
So I started my career as Naran.
I'm no longer licensed.
I only work as a doula and pure companion.
I'm really curious about how we're going
to set this up so that folks like me can
facilitate and be a part of it.
Like you mentioned,
the continuity of relationship I think is
extremely important.
I've had patients that I've clients that
I've worked with for 18 months before
they got on Hospice,
interviewed hospices together,
was there for the deaf,
continue with great support with family
afterwards.
And I don't see that type of relationship
anywhere else in the medical.
And so I think it's extremely important
to figure out how we're gonna set up the
training requirements for folks like me
so that we can not only be present,
but that we'll then be present at the
death too, right?
So that the journey is just,
I think any journey we do is just
preparation for death.
And doulas are uniquely trained to sit
with people in altered states already.
So I would like to talk about that.
Just wanted to jump in again this Jamie.
I also have a role with the Emory Center
for Psychedelics and Spirituality out of
Atlanta Field Scholar with them.
And I,
Kate and I were actually talking about
some of these questions on the way here,
which was I thought was really creative
and Hanifa was we all drove up together
from Santa Fe.
I would love to see the process kind of
Orient around the competencies or the
qualities that are required of the person
in the room rather than thinking in the
other direction from the specialties.
So that's, I,
I find that to be true in the way that
palliative care works and in
transdisciplinary capacity where,
you know, everyone's cross trained and,
but if there's a special expertise that's
needed, you know, high level medical care,
obviously the physician or the nurse.
And if it's a high complex spiritual
distress,
then then spiritual care person and the
social complexities would be a social
worker.
So I would love to see,
I guess to see what are the qualities
that we would want from a person who's in
the space depending on the acuity,
taking the acuity into the consideration
and then think, you know,
the person potentially could be a doula
or could be a chaplain or could be
depending on what experience they're
bringing, right?
So a nurse who's a doula,
that's a different kind of experience
than someone who finished a certificate
program and has no patient care, right?
Or a spiritual care person who has deep
psychedelic experience,
has competencies that a chaplain who
maybe tried cannabis once or something,
you know.
And so I think thinking more about what
is needed in the space and then orienting
the the process around it somehow would
feel patient centered and client centered,
family centered.
So I'm not sure how that could be
accomplished,
but I think it could be that there are
like just potentially like 5 areas of
competency and someone might have three,
they might have two or they might have
one.
And then how do, how do,
how do we bring them up to having the
other four?
That would be needed, you know,
in order to walk in the space in a way
that the,
the state would have confidence that
they're validating this person as
basically a safe person for the level of
acuity and the scope of practice and
everything.
So that's my two cents.
That's great.
Did you have some?
Thank you for that.
That's so great.
And I I'm totally also on board with that.
In our Academy,
we have 25 students right now and we have
several physicians,
we have several nurses,
we have and doctorate, I'm sorry,
spiritual care, spiritual care,
social work, we have MPs, doulas, doulas,
traditional healers, we have doulas.
And so I,
I love that idea of competency and,
and I love to hear from you all who's in,
you know your,
you guys are the members of the Academy.
How because it's being received because
initially, you know, the the thought was,
oh,
it's just for physicians because it's
called conscious physician psychedelis
Academy.
The reason physician is because one who
knows nature.
That's the that's why the verbiage there
and and we're all human.
It's just the remembering of that we are
nature.
And so what's been really phenomenally
mind blowing for me is watching the
blossoming that has happened in our
Academy over the past four months.
Now it's a nine month program and seeing
how each discipline brings so much wisdom
forward.
If it was all physicians, it'd be boring.
We all know the traumas that we carry.
We know the armor that we carry.
We, you know, and,
and it's at first we work on that self
discovery.
We have to do the inner work as
facilitators #1 I don't care what you've
been doing if you haven't.
You could have been using medicine,
psychedelics for decades for recreational
purposes.
And this came up with one of our members.
He said,
I suggested to a friend who has been
using Cell 7 for a long time for
recreational purposes.
And I was like, what do you think about,
you know,
using it for therapeutic purposes?
And he freaked out.
It's like,
I don't think I'm ready for that.
You know, and so it's, it's a,
it's a very great question you're asking.
And if this is just one of many answers,
of course,
but I think having a multidisciplinary
educational program,
we have majority of the individuals who
are in the Academy right now are licensed
and,
and the other tier that we have are
people who have had 1000 hours of client
facing practice that they can show for.
And so that gives me confidence.
And then, and then the screening process,
right?
The screening process is a huge thing.
And we do have practitioners in Southern
New Mexico, Larry,
who are in addiction medicine and they're
like, we have nothing.
This is amazing to be able to give people
the options to be able to utilize well,
the competency I think is a huge thing.
And I think that's, you know,
I and there are ways I'm happy to share
with you.
I've come up with a whole sheet of things
how we would be able to provide education
competency based,
how we would screen people.
We have Indigenous healers in our
community who've been doing this for 30
years, you know, and, and,
and how do we assess that?
And so I think it's a community answer.
It's not an individual answer.
Yeah.
Thank you.
All right.
And then online,
we've got Chris Caldwell again.
Chris,
you should be able to unmute whenever
you're ready.
Yeah, thank you.
I guess I still want to go back and
understand from a pragmatic standpoint.
Can Clinical Chapel.
We, we just lost your audio.
Chris, if you're still talking,
could you try muting and then unmuting on
the mic real quick and see if that does
anything OK And if you could try unmuting
again?
There you go.
Yeah, Thank you.
So did you hear any of my question or
comment?
If you could start over, that'd be good.
Oh, thank you.
OK.
So I still want to go back and understand
from a pragmatic standpoint,
can a clinical chaplain be considered on
the care team and solely support an
individual,
let's say under the direction of a
prescriber, supervision of a prescriber?
Or does it have to be like a clinical
psychotherapist or physician?
This is just my opinion.
I think it's extremely important and kind
of what Jamie is talking about and
Danielle and Lita that we come up with a
pathway so that that can happen because
we have people like, you know,
I think that psilocybin is different than
something like ketamine and that we do
have this whole wide breadth of knowledge
in our community and our state.
And I was talking to Larry, you know,
I went through Naropa and then I went to
look at how to get certified in Colorado
and it was another huge chunk of money,
you know,
and there was all these requirements
after I went through a nine month
training and I'm an RN.
So I would really like to see the people
in our, in our state,
in our community be able to have a
pathway that's a little less clunky than
these other states have done.
And I think it's,
that's really important so that we are
not asking traditional healers that have
been doing this, you know,
it feels really disrespectful to me,
you know,
to have a huge requirement for them to go
through.
So I think what Amy's talking about and
what Lena's talking about with
competencies, you know,
a relatively simple process would be good.
And I'm, and I'm sorry,
I if I said ketamine, I,
I meant psilocybin, but but you were,
you were talking,
you were talking in terms of a pathway.
I guess I just wanted to find out if in
the law a clinical chaplain could be on
the care team now or is that something
that you have to work on?
So Chris, this is Dominic.
You're asking if they can be on the care
team.
And the answer on that is yes.
One of the things that we've been looking
at and at the Training and Education
Committee has been looking at is how to
ensure that individuals,
both who are licensed and unlicensed can
be part of those care teams.
To be able to do the things such as Jen
is talking about respecting those
traditions,
the spiritual practices and so forth,
while still ensuring the safety and
well-being of everybody who's involved.
So yes, they can be on the care team.
Now, depending upon their licensure,
their training and, and all of that,
they may not be able to be the only
individual.
And in fact,
we really wouldn't suggest somebody do it,
just an individual by themselves.
So it would be as a part of a team.
I hope that helps answer your question.
Yeah, because I was,
I was just trying to understand, you know,
to make sure it conforms with the law and,
you know,
to have something ready out of the gate
starting, what, January 1st,
as opposed to having to go back to the
state and try to get them to change the
rules.
So that's, yeah,
that's what I needed to understand.
Thank you.
All right, And next, let's see,
we've got Jen Atma and Jen,
I I belong to your mic.
You can unmute when you're ready.
Yeah, just.
Hi, this is Jen Clemente Katma.
I'm on to.
I'm on my phone and I'm also on my laptop
because I had to run out for an errand.
But when I was looking into this, that I,
I had kind of the same question.
So it looked like,
and I put this comment in,
is that spiritual care can be included?
Yes,
but it has to be LED a clinically LED.
So the clinical supervisor,
whomever that is would opt have that
option to bring in a spiritual care
provider.
So my question is, well, if it's optional,
that means they could obviously leave
them out.
So I was trying to emphasize that it's
important to have them in.
So it seems to be still up to the
discretion of the clinical team lead from
what I understand.
And please correct,
correct me if I'm wrong,
but it didn't really specify who would be
providing the care.
It could be from what I could understand,
and that was sort of the focus of my
presentation in a month or so ago,
is it could either be a chaplain or a or
a doula.
So,
and I'd love to get some clarity on that
because I know we're starting to get down
to the the nuances of this.
So I think Chris, your question is this.
Go ahead.
Sorry, Dominic, go ahead.
That's OK.
Go ahead and finish it, Jen.
No,
I think it was just that if it's a
chaplain, a chaplain is, you know,
pastor has that, you know,
approved clinical chaplain, yes.
So that's kind of one level,
but it's not like only they could do it.
It could be anybody with that sort of
spiritual care or competency layered with
the psychedelic training and I'd love
that.
Again, I'd love the clarity on that.
Well,
I think you just answered your own
question, Jen,
which is really that it has to be
overlaid with the psychedelic and
psilocybin training and somebody who has
that as well.
I don't think the actual designation with
regard to the person at that point really
is the issue.
The one thing I would say is I would
actually push,
and this fits in somebody else said
earlier about the education piece and
making sure to educate communities is
it's not going to be something that's
actually up to the clinician,
especially on a spiritual level.
That's up to the patient and the patient
needs to do that.
And quite frankly,
if a clinician is ignoring the patient's
needs,
including those of the spiritual and
religious nature,
then they're not doing their job.
And so I,
I would actually push that from an
education standpoint,
we need to ensure that patients
understand they have that right to say,
I would like somebody who is following
that spiritual path and will help me in
that path to be a part of my care team.
And thank you, by the way, helpful.
I feel like that we should be a prompt
for that.
That should be sort of built into the
whole intake process much like an IDT
works.
That was my suggestion, sure.
And I think that's a great idea.
James Brown again, sorry.
Back to the question Jen on and I'd love
the tool belt comment.
They consider the back,
I'm a tool belt guy and harm reduction
comes into that.
And so look at this,
think about the day of administration.
Again, I'm real big on this, you know,
whether the day of administration
challenging events that can come up,
right.
And so we're going to prep our
facilitators to sit there and be ready,
but not ready, you know,
and then when it comes up,
there are ratios is a big talk.
And when we look at specifically EOL,
I want everybody to use that filter
ratios, How many people,
how many facilitators per one?
Is it 1 to one?
Your thoughts on who can hold that space?
Because that goes back to again,
the chaplains and who's, you know,
has to be defying those rules and
regulations because those challenging
events can come up.
And is it a 2 to one ratio in your head?
Is it a one to one like envisioned?
I, I've sat in space before.
It's one to one.
I've sat in groups where it's,
it's more than that.
And so I just think about,
I just want everybody to think about that.
And,
and kind of as we think about AOL
specifically,
what can we do to not limit ourselves,
but to allow,
to allow these things to occur and allow
these people to, to act and,
and practice in this space?
I think from a Hospice lens, we,
we do everything as a team.
So we're an interdisciplinary team by
nature.
And I agree with you that it could be 1
to one,
but I think we're going to look at it on
a case by case basis and see what is
needed.
You know,
we're of course going to come at it from
a team standpoint.
And then in Hospice,
we have to utilize our, our doctors,
you know, nursing assessment,
psychological assessment,
and then whoever's going to facilitate.
And that facilitator could be one of
those other people for psilocybin.
I, you know, I think it just depends.
Like if I was gonna facilitate something
on my own away from Hospice,
I would look at the situation and see
what was coming up.
And, you know,
do I feel like I need to have more
support in the room with that person,
you know, or can I hold that space?
And so that's gonna be a piece of that
education around facilitation.
You know, as we're hearing this, I,
I hear several themes going around.
I think we're getting Raymond,
we need to have a team.
We need to have different roles that are
covered, covered there.
We need to have some way of having
continuity through the prep process,
through the journey process,
through the integration and through the
dying there.
I I think the only way that's gonna
happen is by having multiple models
actually signing them out.
People look at that.
I mean,
I think that certain they could have a
model where there's a psychedelic
chaplain who is, you know, by themselves,
you know, you know, one-on-one.
And then there may be like a therapist,
if we have some more training in
psychedelic therapy,
there's other people that could be
reachable within 15 minutes.
I think there's a lot of different models,
but I don't think we're gonna come at it
and we shouldn't come at it with one
model.
I mean,
is everyone saying we have so many
different things?
So I think what we're gonna need to wind
up is say,
what are the roles that are covering and
who can cover the different roles and how
to maintain the continuity.
And that's we're doing this.
No one's done this.
I mean, no one's done this.
And so we're we're creating something new.
And it does feel like we're feeling the
freedom to create an end of life model
and, and focus on that.
So I think this is going to be continuing
conversations here and you hear it coming
around some idealizing doing consensus,
but it's what I thought.
I haven't heard anyone who thinks that
people that are working in a divine
psychedelic role built me from special
trains and they think there's been an
agreement on that.
I don't believe we have,
I don't know what that means.
I, I think that there needs to be,
people need to have the ability to have a
spiritual person there that,
that's something that's, you know,
that's is available.
Easier said than some communities,
but I think that they,
they need to have that available.
And I think the continuity.
So I, I,
I think it's gonna be in a process that
we're going on for months trying to write
out different models.
And in some ways they would just need to
actually start writing out different ways
of different ways of covering them.
I really liked the verbiage that Jamie
just talked about about coming up with
the competencies that we would want to
see like that languaging made a lot of
sense to me, you know,
like this and Lena talking about the
screening process of the people and like
maybe how many hours of patient facing
care have they had in their lives,
you know those kinds of requirements.
Yeah, I'll just jump,
jump back and click for you and say that
what I appreciate about palliative care
model in within the biomedical models
that, you know,
the physician is trained in spiritual
care and the chaplain knows enough about
the social support that, you know,
everyone has a certain basic base level
of competency in all of the areas.
But then some people are more specialized.
I think I said that before,
but that makes sense to me with
psilocybin as well.
So that in southern New Mexico, you know,
it might be like a social worker who has
who has a permission to practice as a
facilitator,
but they have enough training and
spiritual care so that they could work
with.
The one thing that chaplains do is we
collaborate with spiritual and religious
leaders and we know how to bring them in
and sometimes how to kind of nudge them
out, you know, in a sense, if they're not,
if they're not providing kind of
generative support or maybe they're,
you know,
causing distress for some reason.
And just knowing how to assess all of
that and work with all those complex
dynamics as a competency.
But if anyone in the role could have
basic level of spiritual care
competencies,
psychedelic facilitation competencies,
psychotherapeutic, you know, basic,
basic skills,
then it could be any number of people
that could be in that space,
I would think.
Cuz in Colorado,
I was part of the development of the
roles in Colorado and I was living there.
And one thing that we got into is there's
a lot,
there's a wide range of people that will
probably want to be involved in this
eventually,
including like acupuncturists and
physical therapists.
And so how do you,
how do you Orient around what are the
competencies that someone could gain from
any of these different kind of helping
roles and,
and traditional mentors and traditional
healers and peer support leaders and
community organizers and, you know,
create pathways that that people can
brought as broad as possible so that the
access can be brought.
I think one of the competencies, you know,
we've identified the the prep and the
integration is really important to us,
I think, right.
And so identifying the competencies that
go into that, you know,
because one thing in a conversation that
I had with my spiritual care director,
you know,
she feels very equipped to hold space in
a lot of different ways and,
and spiritual concerns that she was
coming up against.
And being faced with potentially this
facilitation piece of sometimes not
feeling equipped to handle deeper therapy
issues, you know,
psychological issues and maybe, you know,
needing more training around integration
and those tools that we want to see
utilized.
And so I think that could be one of the
main,
some of the competencies that we could
look at requiring is those sorts of
skills of holding space in that way.
Thank you.
Thanks for bringing that point up.
And I'm just loving this conversation.
I just got eye drops since that's why I'm
rocking my sunglasses and I'm just pretty
cool.
Also,
I think it's really important for the
state and for the community to understand
because like Larry said,
all of this is new.
Like we're creating a new system,
a new infrastructure,
the importance of communities of practice
that are ongoing so that we can be
learning, OK,
where are we missing support?
Where are we missing competencies when
things are emerging that that we need to
include in the training programs that we
didn't know beforehand.
So a way of supporting communities of
practice around the different care models
for for this individual group will be
really important and something for the
state to invest in in all types of ways.
Yeah,
we're kind of drilling into the meat here.
You know, I like that.
A couple of things that have come to my
mind is the art of listening,
especially with psilocybin compound
sitting in silence for five hours,
you're not feeling like you have to check
your projections into what's going on in
person.
Who is journeying.
There's an impulse that shows up that you
haven't said anything for two or three
hours.
Maybe you need to say something.
And what usually happens is that takes
them out of your experience.
And how do you cultivate a practice of
being a really good listener without
answering questions but mirroring back
what they're asking?
Because it's not what you think it's
important, it's what it means to them.
Mithopters have a wonderful program when
he was working with maths in PTSD studies
that talked about the, you know,
non directed style of guiding,
which I think most of us can agree is
sort of the direction that this is
heading.
And how do you teach practitioners that
style?
Well, it's out there.
The information is out there and
available.
I've gone through the training and it's
not about what you think they need.
It's more about mirroring back to what it
means to them.
Developing that art of being able to take
a question and mirror back to them and
let them answer their own question.
Is is an art takes time to learn those
practices and and you know,
it's something I think I would like to
encourage discussion around as this
program's forward reach out to you know,
these there there are people out there
that are really good at this kind of a
discussion and how to how a facilitator
should conduct themselves during the
session.
So thank you.
Thank you so much for that.
I think that is a huge foundation for
holding space and sitting in that
energetic space with safety with an
individual going through and allowing
them to go through even if you have
discomforts as a facilitator.
And that's why the training takes time.
And I, you know,
in and one of the reasons in our Academy
the first three months is self discovery
is that how do I self reflect?
What is my experience,
the compassionate inquiry that comes from
that?
What is what is self compassion and
sitting in silence and modelling
impractical?
What that looks like.
You know,
some of our members going into retreat
knowing that one of our pillars in
retreat was silence.
In fact,
even during dinner it was mindful eating
and silence and not analyzing or talking
about your experience going inward.
I think the practical piece is huge in
modelling that.
And in fact,
today we had an integration session with
our cohort and one of them said that she
said,
I learned that it's OK to be silent and
she was able to tap into that space again.
And then so I think modeling it and
showing that it is possible and you're
going to make it to be in silence is
really important for facilitation
training.
Thank you so much for that.
That's beautiful.
I also wanted to double check just with
Larry too,
because this is a slightly longer meeting,
so I wanted to see if at any point we
wanted to take like a quick break or
anything.
If you wanted to go all the way to 4:00,
we're coming up on the 2 hour.
Are people up for break?
Great.
OK,
let's take a break for take a 5 day break
then we'll come up back.
All right, we will be back and it's 255.
Right, it is 255.
We're going to find our way back to our
scene.
Lovely conversation.
Thank you everybody.
We are back now and since we've been
focusing a lot on people here in present
in the room,
let's go back to everybody online.
Are there individuals who have questions
who would like to raise their hands and
ask those questions at this, OK,
not seeing anyone online with their hands
raised will come back to the room.
We will check back in online as well
shortly.
This is Danielle Lupesque again.
We've heard a lot of talk about
competencies and pathways,
and I I don't think we have to reinvent
the wheel.
There are some other places we can look
for guidance.
And birth doulas are now eligible for
reimbursement through Medicaid.
The Department of Health has three
different pathways.
Then they can become kind of certified.
In order to be eligible,
they still have to go get an NPI number
and all of that.
But it's,
I'm probably going to quote it wrong,
but one of the pathways was a specific
training program and there are multiple
training programs listed.
Another one was traditional healers.
And you know,
people that have been doing this work
forever,
they get kind of letters of reference and
you know,
they have to prove that they've done X
amount of patients and whatnot.
And there was a third track that I'm not
remembering.
So my point is it would make sense to me
that there are multiple pathways to get
to the point of being a approved
facilitator.
Just thoughts about that.
All right.
And we we, let's see.
I mean, we will.
Well,
I see there there there was an online
hand, but I think it went down.
So you're so Danielle,
I pulled up my New Mexico still at 7
practitioner pathways and MP3.
I've been sitting on this for a while,
you know,
because I I hear you and I think it's so
important what you bring up is such an
important point and it has to be
addressed.
So there's four different,
so licensed clinicians certify secondary
program graduates,
underground facilitators will be
experienced with no licensure and
indigenous practitioners with traditional
knowledge.
And so with each one of them it's going
to be a competency based modular bridge
system.
And there is,
I think it's important for us to define.
The first step is to define core
regulatory competencies.
What does that mean with medical safety
contraindications, trauma,
important care ethics boundaries and on
and on.
But we have this with with either the
state for public comments and and whoever
else is interested in getting this.
The other part of this is that we're
having almost monthly meetings just for
listening sessions through my program so
that the state can't be sitting in and
listening in on the conversation.
And the facilitators on the ground in the
community don't feel that.
They feel safety and confidentiality
without any punitive anything.
So that we have our ear on the ground of
how people are doing this in a really
beautiful way and Safeway,
but they don't feel comfortable coming to
meetings like this and disclosing or
talking about what they're doing.
And so those meetings, you know,
we're we're coming up with the next date.
So you guys will get an e-mail about that.
But in those meetings,
these are the types of things we also
talk about.
So your presence makes a big difference
and your voice makes a big difference.
All right.
And we do have a hand up online,
so I'm going to go to there.
All right, Eric Gertridge,
your mic is enabled.
You can unmute when you're ready.
And as a reminder for that.
OK, Yeah, There you go.
Yeah.
I'm,
I'm calling from New Mexico State
University School of Social Work,
and we're really interested in
incorporating the competencies and the
training and education into a certificate
program as well as just the broader
curriculum for our social work students,
the graduate students in particular.
But my question is,
is there a reason why the chat is
disabled for some people that are
attending and not others?
Not sure about that, unfortunately.
OK,
I just wanted to check and figure out
everything you do.
But yeah, I will.
And we'll see if anything's set different
than you told.
OK, thank you.
I just wanted to express our interest to
the School of Social Work from Las Cruces
and and then that could have been a chat,
but it's disabled on my end, so thank you.
James Brown, again,
just to follow up on that non directive
approach discussion,
I think that this group will have to
decide on is what's considered non
directive approach and what's not.
And that definition will be very
important with the EOL because I think
again in in these competencies,
these core competencies,
bias like bias is going to become big.
And so we need to make sure that our
facilitators are aware of that bias and
that the patient's aware of our own bias
and their own bias so that they can fully
experience that journey and that healing
completely.
And bias does come into that space while
you're helping them with their container.
It really does.
And I'm I'm glad you brought that up.
So just to reiterate that point.
Thank you so much question.
Thank you.
This might be for Dominic or Larry.
I'm just curious for the OR EOL,
are there is there a timeline on
recommendations or or anything that that
will be put forth for public review and
etcetera?
Just if anybody has any insight on that?
No, there's not.
I mean the propagation and education
training have been put forth its first.
And so we're, we're,
we're able to in some ways kind of see
what holds those committees and figure
out didn't play that.
And you know,
we don't have like a deadline to the next
part,
but think we're making good progress.
Hi, hi there.
For some reason my Wi-Fi keeps going out.
I, I guess I'd like to make a,
a suggestion for you, Larry.
A lot of people are coming up with some
really great ideas for rather the
competencies or the topics that really
need to be covered in training.
And you know,
I sat in on the one training session and
they talked about reciprocity.
And so the training organizations they're
looked at,
they're looking at that are already
approved in Colorado and Oregon.
They cover those topics that we've been
talking about.
This is from a general psychedelic
facilitator training perspective,
not from end of life,
but maybe it would be useful to have one
of the organization's talk about what
they're already training on.
Thank you, Chris and I,
I just want to jump back a little bit to
Hanifa's question as far as deadlines.
So as many people know,
we've talked quite a bit in different
meetings that we want to be able to see
in the first patients that they receive
services this next December,
so December 26th.
That does not mean the development and
implementation of the program stops at
that point.
That's the beginning,
the beginning of when patients get seen.
And then as the program continues to
develop,
it will evolve and there will be changes
that occur.
There will be other layers that will be
added.
Not everything is going to necessarily be
in place for those first patients.
We just want to ensure that some patients
are able to be seen.
So when we say that there's not quite a
deadline at this point regarding EOL,
then what that really means is we may by
December have have all of that in place.
But if it takes a little bit longer for
this particular condition, that's OK.
Now I will also say that the individuals
who are in this stage in the end of life,
they're some of the ones who need it the
most.
So my hope is that it is not if it isn't
by December that it's not much longer
after that because we want to ensure to
be able to care for people who need it
the most.
And many of the individuals within AOL,
they're the ones who are going to benefit
from it and they don't have the time.
So we want to ensure that that's there.
But also we recognize that some of the
issues with end of life there is actually
much more complex in different ways.
Not to say that the other conditions
aren't complex,
but there are other considerations to be
made at this point.
And so that may take a little bit longer
time to have some of the aspects
implemented.
I hope that's helpful.
Also real quick for the chat to your
question to Eric, with the chat,
there was a message that we normally
don't have on there that's that says some
people in this chat are outside your
organization and possibly have message
related policies that will apply to the
chat.
So it's some kind of cybersecurity thing
so that we can't change, unfortunately.
I would hope that we're able to have a
situation where, you know, early on,
programs like Jennifer's can get started,
that we can support it.
You have a lot of infrastructure there.
I don't think we need to have a whole
program to be able to come up with a plan
to support you and to be learning as
you're doing that.
I agree.
Yeah, we're going to be ready, I think,
as soon as we get through this program.
September 4th is a graduation date.
So that list of questions over up there,
you guys, we, we, we discussed them all.
They're basically all sort of, you know,
discussed as far as education role.
I mean, it's, I think the,
the most complex thing is these multiple
roles and multiple models to, you know,
keep working on that.
But I think we're making good progress
here.
I mean,
one of my doubts will be to try to draft
up some stuff in writing and share it to
people.
And so we can start, you know,
having things that are moving towards,
you know, rules and agreements.
And we'll do that over the next few
months.
We don't have to say Earl's work yet.
We need ourselves that time to be kind of
spacious.
So whenever we feel like we're we're done.
I think we've done a lot of great work
today that no one's holding people early
work.
I think we want to hang out Barry and and
I say that September 4th is our
graduation, Jennifer,
but we we do have to submit to the state
for the program to be a certified pathway.
So that's that's another piece to it that
I believe that is in full is in the fall,
the submission for training.
So the next step as far as rules and
regulations,
we're right now going through cultivation.
The next step is the training and
education.
So some of it will depend exactly on when
those rules are fully developed,
put out to the public,
go through the rule hearing.
But our goal is to have that finished by
fall.
OK, OK.
So yeah, we'll, we'll keep on track.
Thank you so much.
And I just want to check in with
everybody online.
Do we have additional questions or topics
to be raised from anyone online not
seeing any at this point.
Danielle.
Hello, Danielle.
Again,
when you said there are special
considerations around the end of life,
what came up for came up for me is that I
currently have a couple of clients that I
would not who want to facilitate a
journey in their home, in their space.
And that's where Hospice care is
generally given.
There are some people that are in
facilities that wouldn't allow it.
What are people's thoughts around that?
Like that's in it's in settings.
It's a big deal.
And some of these settings are not really
conducive to enlightening juries.
Like I have some thoughts of it.
Thank you.
That's excellent question.
So Anita here again,
and I think that there's a lot to,
it's a complex question,
but one I always say that the medicine is
always good.
And so if you're working with limited
setting parameters, you know,
you can use things like music and line
folds to help induce the stimulation to A
to a degree,
which can also then be helped and
supported by whoever's in the
facilitation team.
But if that's the only option, right,
like that client is bed bound or like
that's where it has to happen,
then I think if they want to do it and
they want to do it in their home,
you have to kind of just being the place
of emergence and allowance.
Yeah,
that's the sort of like my initial
response to that.
Now this is Kate again.
You know,
we're getting down to these real
questions.
And I think as far as the regulations go,
they're going to have certain
requirements and certain minimums,
like it has to be an approved setting.
And so for Hospice, I think in general,
it's there's a consensus that in a home
can be an approved setting.
But is a particular home a good approved
setting where you would do it,
your Hospice would do it.
So there are those.
I don't think any facilitator should be
forced to be in a space they don't feel
good about.
So just because you know the regulation
stay at home could be approved,
would it mean that you would have to
approve of a certain home?
On the other hand,
what other options might there be and
there will be other facilities that are
approved.
So I think all this network,
all these pieces are getting developed
and and coming together.
I just wondered if it agree me if this
microphone it's kind of OK that works.
I agree with what if it's in a
neighborhood where there's trucks driving
by and there's outside noise and you have
no way of controlling that and we're all
looked looking for, you know,
an optimal experience.
If perhaps someplace could be found in
different locations that could be booked
for a session day if the person is able
and willing to be transported,
that's a possibility.
Or is it worth consideration on the TOH
side that?
We'll send out a message with some
meetings and with some meeting dates in
in May.
I think we had a talk.
I believe May.
There's May 8th or 15th or Fridays.
Let's take a look, see what else?
Yeah, yeah.
So May 15th.
Oh, I see.
Well, yeah,
get into the thing where I can see the
other calendars and not me.
Yep.
Unless there's any reason not to.
Let's May 8th as our next end of life
committee meeting.
One to three.
Let's see, there is another committee.
Somebody got that already?
Yeah.
Training and education,
unless you want to see if they want to do
a joint because a lot of the questions
coming up, sorry, yeah,
since a lot of the questions coming up
right now are about competencies and
training,
would that be something we could check
with Brenda,
who is the chair of that committee to see
about doing it as a joint combined to
talk a little bit more about some of
those aspects?
I, I look good.
That sounds good people on board.
OK, we'll, we'll,
we'll finagle that with Brenda.
We'll talk with her.
And if it does not,
then the 15th the afternoon is open at
this time.
I, I like the joint committee.
I do would be 3 or 5.
That meeting is from 1:00 to 3:00.
While we're waiting,
anybody else on line who has questions or
issues, concerns, want to raise your hand?
No.
OK, Larry, back to you.
I think the meeting is adjourned here.
Enjoy the rest of your afternoon.
Thanks so much for everybody for coming
down.
A lot of people came down Santa Fe and
around the state.
So thank you.
And Jennifer, awesome presentation.
Thanks for getting us, getting us,
and just on behalf of the department,
I really would like to thank everybody
for being here.
It's these meetings that really help us
to be able to get the information that we
need to be able to move forward and have
an absolute excellent program.
I also would like to just thank everybody,
particularly in the room for helping
Jorge to get his steps in today.
Valuable to be in the room together.
Yes, thank you, everybody.
Thank you, Johnny.
Well, oh, that was that was Danielle.
Thank you, Danielle.
Danielle.